<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Reflections upon the bulls of the Popes Paul the Third and Pius the Fifth emitted against King Henry the 8 and Queen Elizabeth of England.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1686</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B09866</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R724A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R232036</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">61297142</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 61297142</idno>
            <idno type="VID">180657</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B09866)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 180657)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2839:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Reflections upon the bulls of the Popes Paul the Third and Pius the Fifth emitted against King Henry the 8 and Queen Elizabeth of England.</title>
                  <author>Philotheus.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year 1686.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Philotheus.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication suggested by Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Includes errata on p. 12 at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Henry --  VIII, --  King of England, 1491-1547.</term>
               <term>Elizabeth --  I, --  Queen of England, 1533-1603.</term>
               <term>Pius --  V, --  Pope, 1504-1572.</term>
               <term>Paul --  III, --  Pope, 1468-1549.</term>
               <term>Bulls, Papal.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  History --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:180657:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Reflections upon the BULLS OF THE POPES PAUL THE THIRD, AND PIUS THE FIFTH, Emitted againſt KING HENRY The 8. And QUEEN ELIZABETH OF ENGLAND.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1686.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:180657:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:180657:2"/>
            <head>TO The Right Honourable and truly Noble JAMES EARL OF PERTH, LORD DRUMMOND, &amp;c. <hi>LORD HIGH</hi> CHANCELLOUR OF SCOTLAND.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is nothing ſo much amuſeth theſe out of the Communion of the <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> as the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed guilt of Diſloyalty, maliciouſly fixed upon the <hi>Roman Catholick Religion:</hi> Nor is there any thing more confirms this unhappy prejudice in the Hearts of Honeſt and Loyal Subjects in theſe Kingdoms, then the <hi>Bulls</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:180657:3"/>damnatory Sentences iſſued out by the Popes, <hi>PAUL</hi> the Third and <hi>PIUS</hi> the Fifth, againſt King <hi>HENRY</hi> the Eigth, and Queen <hi>ELIZABETH</hi> of <hi>England:</hi> Now untill this great miſtake be removed, the Subjects divide amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and ill Blood is Nouriſhed, to the intollerable dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of his <hi>MAJESTY,</hi> whoſe Intereſt is the leſs ſecured while ſo dangerous an <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> is unjuſtly charged on <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick</hi> Subjects, and no vindication made to wipe off ſo foul a Crime: For if a <hi>Catholick</hi> Prince must not trust his <hi>Catholick</hi> Subjects, he muſt give only credit to theſe who would have the municipal Statutes of this Kingdom, made upon politick conſiderations, unalterable and irreverſible, never to be repealed upon the fairest emergencies, and just<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est reflections, that after Ages may make for the diſcovery of conceived prejudices, which were to bind up the hands of Princes in the prudent management of their Affairs, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrict their ſupreme Right of Legiſlation. <hi>My LORD.</hi> I have adventured to vindicate the <hi>Church Catholick</hi> from ſo deſtructive a Doctrine in as few Words as the ſubject mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter could allow off: And ſince none hath ſuffered the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere laſhes of viperous Tongues more then Your <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> for that the <hi>Catholick</hi> Religion is joined in your Perſon with that great truſt repoſed in you, and yet far beyond the leaſt tincture or ſuſpicion of Diſloyalty, I thought none fitter to ſhelter and protect this ſmall Eſſay then Your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> I give it then up, <hi>My LORD,</hi> to Your Patronage, and Tui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in the protection whereof you will demean your ſelf as a true <hi>SON</hi> of the Holy <hi>Cacholick Church,</hi> and juſtifie the Honeſt and Religious ſervice of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute> 
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt oblidges and moſt Humble Servant. <hi>Philotheus</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:180657:3"/>
            <head>Some Reflections on the Bulls of PAUL THE THIRD, AND PIUS THE FIFTH, Emitted againſt KING HENRY The 8. And QUEEN ELIZABETH OF ENGLAND.</head>
            <p>THE Chriſtians of the Roman Catholick Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion believe nothing as matter of Faith, but what the Univerſal Church practiſes, or a General Council by its Decrees oblidges to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve as ſuch; And ſince neither the Church Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick in diffuſion, or repreſentation practiſes, or by Her Cannons enjoyns as matters of Faith, <hi>viz.</hi> That its Lawful for Popes upon the Heads of Hereſie, Schiſm, or ſcandalous iniquity to Excommunicate Kings and abſolute
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:180657:4"/>Princes, and thereupon to abſolve their natural Subjects from their neceſſary alledgeance, its the higheſt injuſtice to impoſe this on the Catholick Religion as an Article of Faith.</p>
            <p>To clear this, let us firſt confider what is the practice of the Church diffuſive in this affair: Its plain that this dangerous Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine ſo deſtructive to Humane Societies is diſowned by all Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Princes and Monarchs, guarding ſufficiently againſt it by their Imperial and Royal Laws, and Conſtitutions: How do the Italian Princes debate their Temporal Intreſts with Popes who ſometimes quarrel with them, and defend their ſecular Rights by the Sword? And who more eagerly and vigourouſly vindicates his Royal prerogative in Temporal concerns againſt all the pretentions of Popes, then the <hi>French</hi> King? And its as evident that the Emperour, the Spaniſh and Polonian Princes by their municipal Laws aſſert their Imperal and Royal Rights againſt all mortals. And as this is the practiſe of Catholick Princes, ſo is it of the particular Churches within their Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions and Teritories, for they in their Eccleſiaſtical Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions declare the independency of their abſolute Princes in Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porals, and that the Church cannot pretend by vertue of the power of the Keyes directly, or indirectly to diveſt any abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Prince or Monarch of his Royal Rights and Priviledges: Look to the Cannons of the late <hi>Gallican National</hi> Aſſembly, and to the Univerſities of <hi>Rehemes, Caen, Poictiers, Valence, Bordeaux, Bourges,</hi> &amp;c. And to the whole Colledge of <hi>Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon,</hi> condemning <hi>Sanctarellus</hi> his propoſitions, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Pope might for Schiſm or Hereſie depoſo Princes, and exempt Subjects from their Alledgeance: And tho' this Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine be charged maliciouſly upon the generality of the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> yet a provincial Councel of that Order cauſed publickly to burn <hi>Mariana</hi> his Book for handling problematically that of kill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Kings, and this Society in all the Catholick Territories, where they are ſcattred, do generally renounce that Doctrine ſo fatal to Civil Authority, elſe they ſhould not have ſo eaſie an acceſs to the Courts of Princes, and find with them ſuch kind receptions as they daily do.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:180657:4"/>
Secondly. There is no Authority from a general Council that allows of this dangerous Doctrine, nor is there any thing like it to be found in the laſt general Counſel held at <hi>Trent,</hi> in which are all theſe Articles that oblidge the Catholicks as matters of Faith, nor in any other general Counſel prior to that, ſave what, is ignorantly concluded from a Decree of the <hi>Lateran</hi> Council held under <hi>Innocent</hi> 3. But to free this Counſel of any thing that looks like that unhappy Doctrine: Let us no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice firſt, There were preſent at this Convention held at the <hi>Lateran</hi> the Emperours of the Eaſt and Weſt, the Kings of <hi>England, France, Hungary, Jeruſalem, Cyprus, Arragon,</hi> &amp;c. By their Ambaſſdors, ſayes <hi>Mattheus Pariſienſis,</hi> who all might have agreed together to have purged their Territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and Dominions from the Heretical crew of the <hi>Walden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> and <hi>Albigenſes,</hi> ſo that by this compact amongſt abſolute Princes they might have conſented upon their faileure, if not concurring to exterminate the Hereticks, that at the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es Sentence the guilty ſhould forfeit his Dominion and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty, and the party performing receive it: And this is as warrantable as the Convention made by the confederate Princes at <hi>Smalcad.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly. The Perſons here threatned to loſe their Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories and Properties are termed by the Decree, <hi>Domini prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipales,</hi> and certainly by theſe the Church never underſtood abſolute Princes, but only-petty and Feudatory Lords, who being Superiors over other <hi>Vaſſals,</hi> had a Dominion <hi>directum</hi> over them to which Lords the <hi>Vaſſals</hi> owed Fidelity, and with that ſometime Subjection, as many do in <hi>Germany.</hi> And of theſe allenerly are the Words of the <hi>Lateran</hi> Decree to be underſtood, and not of the Imperial or Regal Dignities, who <hi>ob eminentiam dignitatis,</hi> are ſtill excepted from the higheſt cenſures of the Church, as you ſhall hear anon.</p>
            <p>Thirdly. Its more then propable that the <hi>Domini princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pales</hi> there expreſt were chiefly, if not only the Feudatory petty Superiors, who ſupported the <hi>Albigenſes,</hi> continued
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:180657:5"/>the Hereſie and Crocked the Wars. Such as the Earls of <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſe, Foix, Comminges,</hi> and Prince of <hi>Bern,</hi> all Protectors of theſe Rebellious Hereticks, and it was upon the ſcore of this <hi>Lateran</hi> Decree that <hi>Montferret</hi> was inveſted in the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periorties and Territories of <hi>Tholouſe</hi> after the Victorious ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of the Catholick Princes had againſt theſe confederate Nobles.</p>
            <p>Let me add further that in the foreſaid Decree there is no mention had of <hi>Reges,</hi> but of <hi>Domini,</hi> or of <hi>Regna,</hi> but <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram,</hi> which certainly relate to the Lands and Poſſeſſions of the petty Feudatory Lords.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, To ſum up all, upon ſuppoſition that the Counſel ſo determined, that the Cenſure ſhould reach all Dignities of the higheſt Quality (which is morally inpoſſible to think that ſuch abſolute powers ſhould conſent to their own ruin.) yet ſtill it muſt be conſidered that this Decree did relate only to a matter of Diſcipline or Eccleſiaſtick Government, in which caſes the Church pretends not to Infallibility, for ſhe alters her Government when inavoidable inconveniencies appear: For had that Decree been of Faith, the <hi>Tridentine</hi> Council had not paſſed it by without a determination, eſpecially ſince be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Seſſion of that Synod the Hereticks frequently charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this ſcandalous Doctrine upon the Roman Catholick Church: Yea had that <hi>Lateran</hi> Decree reſpected the higheſt Powers without exception, and the Decree being of Faith, then how could the whole Univerſity at <hi>Paris,</hi> April 20. 1626. have condemned <hi>Sanctarelleus</hi> propoſition? Or how could the Colledge of <hi>Sorbon</hi> together with the Provincial Councel of the <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> the ſuppoſed aſſerters of the Popal Authority over Kings, have ſubſcribed the ſaid condemnation to the great ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of the Parliament of <hi>Paris?</hi> Certainly if the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teran</hi> Decree was of Faith, and extended to imperial and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Dignities, then all the aforeſaid Perſons muſt have been Heretical for condemning that propoſition of dethroning Princes in caſe of Hereſie, Schiſm, or ſome enorme crime: Yea how
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:180657:5"/>could Popes themſelves judicially in the meetings of Cardinals at <hi>Rome</hi> have cenſured the Books of <hi>Bellarmine, Becan,</hi> and others for aſſerting the Popes power of depoſing Princes as aforeſaid? If before this in the <hi>Lateran</hi> it had been matter of Faith.</p>
            <p>We come now to conſider ſome particular inſtances alleadg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for proving this Doctrine to be of Faith in the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, ſuch as the Bulls of <hi>Paul</hi> 3. againſt <hi>Henry</hi> 8, and of <hi>Pius</hi> 5. againſt Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> wherein not only theſe are excommunicated, and their Subjects adhear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to them, ſtruck with the ſame Sentence, but all Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Subjects are alſo abſolved from their alledgeance; and all Catholick Powers and Dignities abroad commanded under pain of Excommunication, not to correſponde, tranſact, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with them: They are alſo required to invade theſe Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated Princes: The Popes giving the Invaders full power thereto. In anſwer to theſe ſad inſtances, its replyed by all True and Honeſt Catholicks. that they cannot juſtifie the miſdemeanours of particular Popes, who through miſ-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation pick or humour have adventured to do ſomethings that are unaccountable, ſince God hath given no promiſe of an infallible direction to them in all the Inſtances of their Life, nor hath any Catholick of the moſt wild and roving Humour dared to plead for their impeccability in their perſonalor principal Actions, that being proper for Angels and the Spirits of juſt Men made perfect. However, ſince theſe of the Papal Dignity have the Honour of ſo great and venerable a Character as to be the Chief Biſhops of the Church Catholick, and to be Temporal Princes likewiſe, it were the higheſt indiſcretion, to put a groſs and ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous conſtruction upon their Actions without conſidering what were the motives that moved them, and meaſures they uſed in a matter that ſeems ſo Offenſive to the World, and Deſtructive or Humane Society; and if ye but regard and conſider the ſpecial care the Divine Providence has had of that <hi>See</hi> above all the particular Churches and Societies in the World, it
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:180657:6"/>would fright any modeſt and humble Man, from paſſing a raſh and ſevere Cenſure againſt the Supream Governours of that Church: Notice but how the whole Chriſtian World near from the Infancy of Chriſtianity was divided into three Patriarchates, whereof the chief and the moſt powerful was the Weſtern Church, and the Seat thereof <hi>Rome,</hi> to this all had anciently recourſe, ſaith <hi>Ireneus,</hi> and in ſo farr was the Churches Unity preſerved, for that the particular Churches lived in Conjunction with this, which was founded by the two chief Apoſtles. St. <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> to the firſt of which the Circumciſion, and to the ſecond the Incircumciſion was chiefly committed, ſo that the whole Chriſtian World being eminent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intruſted to theſe two, and their charge tranſmitted to the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> their Succeſſors, theſe eminent vaſt truſts conſpire in this Apoſtolick <hi>See:</hi> And tho' Infallibility were not allowed to that particular <hi>See,</hi> yet certainly indefectabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity cannot in juſtice be denyed it, for we ſee <hi>defacto,</hi> all the Churches of Apoſtolick Foundation have failed, and their Succeſſions interrupted, this only remaining entire, and unleſs we have recourſe to Her for the determination of Contraver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies relating to Faith, according to the Rule of the Fathers, it ſhall not be poſſible to diſtinguiſh Catholick Truth, from He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie: <hi>Tertullian</hi> particularly tells us in his Book of <hi>Preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> that the only way left the Church by which She ſhould diſtinguiſh Hereſie, from Truth, was to have recourſe <hi>ad Eccleſias matrices,</hi> and, thereto enquire if ſuch Doctrines were derived down to them from the Apoſtolick Foundation: Now ſince there is no Church in exiſtence of an Apoſtolick Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation whoſe Succeſſion hath not been interrupted, ſave that of <hi>Rome,</hi> we muſt needs then have recourſe to Her for ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tling us in matters of Faith, otherwiſe the Fathers Rule is not practicable, and no means left by God to ſecure us Infallibly from Errour: So that not only the Indefectibility of that <hi>See;</hi> but the greatneſs of its principality, and the Wiſdom of its Clergy, the confluence of Nations towards Her, and the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:180657:6"/>protection of all the Catholick Princes beſtowed on Her, all theſe ſhould ſtrongly oblidge us not to paſs indiſcreetly and raſhly a Cenſure upon the Actions of its chief Governour.</p>
            <p>But to come to the inſtances, its anſwered that the Bull given out by <hi>Paul</hi> 3 againſt <hi>Henry</hi> 8, was concerning a matter of ſecular intreſt or plea of Law, for the ground of the Popes ſentence was from that unwarantable deed done by <hi>John of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> who made a reſignation of his Crown to the <hi>See of Rome,</hi> and <hi>England Feudatory</hi> and himſelf a <hi>Vaſſall</hi> to that <hi>See,</hi> which deed tho its moſt certain was <hi>ab origine</hi> null and void, he having no power to alienate his Royal hereditary Rights to any in prejudice of his Lawful Heirs and Succeſſors, yet the Apoſtolick <hi>See</hi> having had ſuch a grant made to them, ſeveral of her Biſhops continued the claim of Superiority upon the ſaid Title, And it was certainly upon this head, that <hi>Paul</hi> 3 proceeded againſt <hi>Henry</hi> 8, who had by Act of Parliament renounced all Forreign Jutiſdiction, by which <hi>Paul</hi> the third Judged the Apoſtolick <hi>See,</hi> and St. <hi>Peters</hi> Patrimony prejudged, and thereupon treated <hi>Henry</hi> 8. as his <hi>Vaſſall</hi> and abſolved his Subjects from their alledgeance, and requiring all Catholick Princes to concurr to the reducing him as a Rebel, who denyed fidelity to the Apoſtolick <hi>See</hi> his ſuppoſed temporal Lord. Its known to all that ever read the Engliſh Hiſtory that there were great heats between the Roman <hi>See</hi> and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Kings, upon this pretended Title of the reſignation, The Pope ſtill requiring Fidelity mid other Feudatory duties from <hi>England,</hi> which were ever Juſtly denyed, Several Laws and Statutes being made in <hi>England</hi> to guard them againſt that unjuſt Title. And to make this appear more evident that <hi>Paul</hi> the 3 treated <hi>Henry</hi> the 8 in this Bull as his ſuppoſed <hi>Vaſſal,</hi> read but the Words of the Bull, <hi>Sect.</hi> 15. Where the Pope command's all that were below an Imperial and Regal Dignity, not to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpond, converſe, or tranſact, with <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, or his Accomplices, or Favourers, under pain of Excomunication, but as for the Imperial and Regal Dignites, he only beſeeches
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:180657:7"/>and exorts them ſo to do without threatning any ſuch Cenſure, thus runs the Bull <hi>(praeterea ad dictum Henricum Regem fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilius ad ſanitatem, &amp; praefatae ſedis obaedientiam reducen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, omnes &amp; ſingulos Chriſtianos principes, quâcunque etiam Imperiali &amp; regali dignitate fulgentes per viſcera miſerecor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diae Dei noſtri (cujus cauſa agitur) hortamur &amp; in dommo requirimus, eis nihil ominus, qui imperatore &amp; Rege inferio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res fuerint, quos propter exellentiam dignitatis à cenſuris ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipimus, ſub excomunicationis paenâ mandantes, ne Henrico regi ejuſque complicibus,</hi> &amp;c) Where its plain and undiſput<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to any, ſafe quibling Lawyers, that Imperial and Regal Dignities are ſtill excepted from the great Cenſure of Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, and that <hi>propter eminentiam dignitatis,</hi> ſo that <hi>Paul</hi> the Third in his Bull, looked on <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, as Feudatory to himſelf and the Apoſtolick <hi>See,</hi> and as no abſolute Prince, tho' he was infinitely wrong in ſo judging: From all this it follows that the Pope dealt with <hi>Henry</hi> the Eigth, in a matter reputed Secular and Temporal, and they Acted one againſt another as Temporal Princes, contending violently for their ſecular Rights and concerns, in which mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters all Mankind, Pope, and all may Err, and the true Holy and Catholick intreſt remain entire and ſecure, and Catholick Princes are no worſe Sons of the Church for maintaining their Rights and Priviledges againſt all whatſoever: Truly, this grant of King <hi>John's</hi> as it was Originally void and null, ſo it was done by a moſt undeſerving Governour, who neither knew nor had care of his own Intreſt, who was guilty of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion againſt his Father and Brother, and who murthered his Nephew to uſurp the Crown, who loſt alſo all the Engliſh Intreſt, either by conqueſt or matches in <hi>France,</hi> not to ſpeak of his Irreligion and Atheiſm: And as this grant was Originally null and done by ſo unworthy a Prince, ſo it was ſoon revoked by his Succeſſors in Parliament, who in ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt a matter would have been Highly prejudged, the very Catholick Clergy deteſting the Pope for the ſevere and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:180657:7"/>courſes againſt <hi>England,</hi> becauſe of that Title, as the Biſhops of <hi>Durham, Wincheſter, Norwich, &amp;c.</hi> Yea the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> then a Cardinal and Legate, being at <hi>Rome,</hi> when a Charter adorned with a Golden Bull was preſented at the High Altar in preſence of the King, the ſaid Prelate ſtept in, as the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Dublin</hi> had done at the firſt grant, and in Name of the Clergy and Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> produced at the ſame Altar his appeals, and all the <hi>Peers</hi> accorded with him therein: How did EDWARD the Firſt reſiſt the claim of the after Popes? and in ED<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>WARD the Third's time did <hi>England</hi> ſecure their Right by Act of Parliament, where were Prelates, Lords, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, againſt all the Papal pretenſions: Yea a Parliament was held at <hi>London</hi> 1214, being the Year after the Grant, where the Arch-Biſhop ſat as Preſident with all the Clergy and Laity, and there by command of the Pope, the Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Fealty and Hommage, by which the King was oblidged to the Pope, was abſolutely releaſed on the 7. of <hi>July:</hi> So that Catholick Princes have ſtill vindicated their Rights againſt the higheſt Powers of the Church, and yet judged no Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks upon the matter.</p>
            <p>Lets now conſider <hi>Pius</hi> 5 his Bull againſt Queen <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> Its true there he declares to all Catholick ſubjects that ſhe is no true Princeſs and abſolves her Subjects from their allegiance, but upon good ground, for firſt conſider that if <hi>Mary</hi> Queen of <hi>England</hi> lawfully ſucceeded King <hi>Edward</hi> her Brother: then <hi>Elizabeth</hi> could have no Title, as my Lord <hi>Beacon</hi> acknowledged <hi>H:</hi> 7: <hi>p.</hi> 206: (the legitimation of Queen <hi>Mary</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth</hi> are incompatible) unleſs ye juſtifie both the marriages, which no Chriſtian will adventure, and the Kingdom not being Elective, in that caſe <hi>Mary</hi> Queen of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> ſhould in all Juſtice have ſucceeded. <hi>Pius</hi> 5th in his Bull ſaith <hi>Queen Mary</hi> of <hi>England</hi> is legitimat (<hi>uſu namque verae religionis, quam ab illius deſertore Henrico</hi> 8, <hi>olim everſam,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:180657:8"/>Clarae mem: Maria regina legitima, hujus ſedis praeſidio reparaverat, &amp;c.</hi> now ſince <hi>Mary Queen</hi> of <hi>England</hi> is acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged the true Child by this Pope, Then was <hi>Elizabeth</hi> an natural: all the Lords and Commons in a Parliament in <hi>England</hi> held after the Death of <hi>Edward</hi> 6. acknowledged <hi>Mary</hi> for their Soveraign, and that the marriage of her Mother was good and ſtood with Gods Law and moſt Holy Word; which was this ſame thing as to ſay that <hi>Elizabeth</hi> was illegitmate, and LUTHER the great Reformer deemed her ſo too, ſays <hi>Osburn</hi> Mem: <hi>Q: Eliz; p.</hi> 5. Yea look to the date of her birth as its in my Lord <hi>Herberts, H:</hi> 8. <hi>p.</hi> 350. which was in September the 7. 1533, while Queen <hi>Catherines</hi> divorce was pronounced by <hi>Cranmer,</hi> the Kings Caſuiſt and judge apoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for that end, the 23. of <hi>May</hi> proceeding, ſo that her Mother was then quick whilſt <hi>Henry</hi> 8. was yet Husband to Queen <hi>Catherine,</hi> which continued till the tearm of that Sentence: I know <hi>Stow, Speed,</hi> and others alledge a private Mariage between <hi>Henry</hi> 8. and <hi>Anna Bullen, Elizabeth,</hi> Mother, on <hi>January</hi> 25, yet ſtill <hi>Elizabeth</hi> is born within ſeven months and a few odd dayes, by which wee may gueſs at the Honeſty of her Mother who brought forth <hi>Elizabeth</hi> into the World as vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, luſty, and healthful, as others uſe to be at the end of nine months. If it be ſaid that the Pope innodates her not for her unjuſt Title, but for her Religion; to this its anſwered firſt, that its evident in that the Pope declared Queen <hi>Mary</hi> legitimate, he muſt have looked on <hi>Elizabeth</hi> as an unjuſt uſurper, for its impoſſible to reconcile to them both a juſt Title of Succeſſion, yea <hi>Pius</hi> 5. in his Bull calls her <hi>praetenſa angliae Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gina) the pretended Queen of</hi> England, and ſo not the true.</p>
            <p>Secondly. The ſad and Unnatural, Inhumane and diſhonourable uſage done by <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> to Queen <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> keeping Her under reſtraint and in cloſe Priſon, moved the Pope to conceal Queen <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Scotland</hi> Her juſt Title, (of which he was fully perſwaded) leſt the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:180657:8"/>thereof might haſten the fatal ſtroke which at length befel Her.</p>
            <p>Thirdly. When the Inhumanity which Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> uſed againſt her Couſin Queen <hi>Mary</hi> was noyſed abroad the World over, then did <hi>Pius</hi> the fifth ſend <hi>Ridulph</hi> a <hi>Florentine</hi> to Conſult with the Catholicks in <hi>England</hi> to an inſurrection againſt <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> upon which followed the riſing in Arms in the North; and tho the Catholick Lords did in their Declaration mention Religion, yet the true cauſe was the ſetling Queen <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Scotland</hi> the true and undoubted Heireſs of <hi>England,</hi> and the Lords propoſing Religion then, did <hi>ipſo facto</hi> imply the alteration of Religion and Government together, and upon the advancing of the Catholick Religion followed the intreſt of Queen Mary, ſo that the Pope and Catholick Lords did in this as the memorable General <hi>Monk</hi> did in carrying on the Loyal deſign of reſtoring our late Soveraign King <hi>Charles</hi> II. not daring to expreſs his Name, leaſt it ſhould have marred and ruined his honeſt purpoſes.</p>
            <p>Fourthly. <hi>Cambden</hi> tells us 1569. p. 160, that <hi>Leonard Deackers</hi> ſecond Son to the Lord <hi>Deackers</hi> of <hi>Gyſland,</hi> under took the delivery of Queen <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> who then was in <hi>Derbyſhire</hi> in my Lord <hi>Shrewsburrys</hi> keeping, and my Lord <hi>Northumberland</hi> was cheif complotter in this deſign, and he alſo was chief Commander of the inſurrection of the North, who as all know intended nothing ſo much as Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s Title, tho' in the Declaration of War he Judged fit to conceal and not expreſs it. From all this then its clear that the Pope in his Bull againſt <hi>Elizabeth</hi> deſigned chiefly the ſetling of the righteous Heir, and he looked on <hi>Elizabeth</hi> not only as an uſurper, but as a Heretical Subject alſo, whom all were to avoid, becauſe of her Hereſie, and not to yeild obedience or alledgeance becauſe of her unjuſt Title; and in all this affair the Pope act<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d nothing againſt the Faith and Doctrine of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church, or the true Properties, Intreſts, and Priveledges, of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:180657:9"/>Chriſtian Princes, but rather evidenced his paternal care in ſecuring the Rights and concerns of Monarchs, and ſuppreſſing of uſurping and unjuſt Powers, to which he might concurr not only as a Ghoſtly Father by his Spiritual advices and cenſures, but as a Temporal Prince gave aid and aſſiſtance to ſetle and repoſeſs Lawful, and righteous Heires thruſt from their legal Rights.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA's.</head>
            <p>Page <hi>2.</hi> l. <hi>15.</hi> for Imperal r. Imperial, Page <hi>4.</hi> l. <hi>1.</hi> for Crocked r. broched, l. <hi>29.</hi> for Popal r. Papal Page <hi>5.</hi> l. <hi>24.</hi> for principal r. private Page <hi>6.</hi> l. <hi>16.</hi> for indefectability r. indefectibility l. <hi>17.</hi> for <hi>defacto</hi> r. <hi>de facto</hi> Page <hi>7.</hi> l. <hi>20.</hi> for requiring r. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired Page <hi>8.</hi> l. <hi>1.</hi> for exorts r. exhorts <hi>Page 10.</hi> l. <hi>16.</hi> for tearm r. term</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
